Robert Kleiman Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Robert Kleiman Papers 1935-1983 1943-1945
MSS85471
Kleiman, Robert, 1918-2004
5,000 items
15 containers plus 1 classified and 9 oversize
8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Journalist. Correspondence, memoranda, propaganda material including leaflets, newspapers, printed matter, and ephemera, interrogations of prisoners of war, reports, newsletters, newspaper clippings, and other papers relating chiefly to Kleiman's service with the United States Office of War Information during World War II and pertaining to psychological warfare and the use of propaganda in the Far East, with a much smaller portion reflecting his work as a journalist before and after the war.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Fisher, Francis McCracken, 1907-2000. Yenan reports. 1944-1945.; Kleiman, Elnora H., 1917-1998--Correspondence.; Kleiman, Robert, 1918-2004.; MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964.; Marquardt, Frederic S. (Frederic Sylvester), 1905- --Correspondence.; Monroe, Barbara R.--Correspondence.; Rickenbacker, Eddie, 1890-1973.; Shulman, Marshall Darrow--Correspondence.
Organizations
Allied Forces. South West Pacific Area.; China. Lu jun.; United States. Army. Army, 6th.; United States. Army. Forces in China-Burma-India Theater.; United States. Office of War Information.; Zhongguo guo min dang.
Subjects
Chinese--Philippines--Luzon.; Guerrillas--Philippines--Luzon.; Japanese--Philippines.; Journalism.; Kachin (Asian people)--Burma.; Propaganda, American--Asia.; Propaganda, American--Europe.; Propaganda, American--Philippines.; Propaganda, American.; Propaganda, Japanese--Philippines.; Psychological warfare.; Reconstruction (1939-1951)--Burma.; World War, 1939-1945--Burma.; World War, 1939-1945--China.; World War, 1939-1945--East Asia.; World War, 1939-1945--India.; World War, 1939-1945--Japan.; World War, 1939-1945--Oceania.; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners and prisons.; World War, 1939-1945--Propaganda.; World War, 1939-1945--Psychological aspects.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.
Places
Assam (India)--History.; Burma--History--1824-1948.; China--History--1937-1945.; Europe--Colonies--Asia.; Europe--Foreign relations--1945-; Europe--Foreign relations--United States.; India--History--British occupation, 1765-1947.; Leyte Island (Philippines)--History.; Manila (Philippines)--History.; New Guinea--History--20th century.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.; Philippines--History--Japanese occupation, 1942-1945.; Philippines--Newspapers.; United States--Foreign relations--1945-1989.; United States--Foreign relations--Europe.; Yan'an Shi (China)--History.
Titles
Free Philippines (Manila, Philippines: Airborne ed.); Leyte shimbun.; Leyte-Samar bulletin.; Leyte-Samar free Philippines.; Manila free Philippines.; Voice of freedom (Radio program); Voice of victory.
Occupations
Journalists.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Robert Kleiman, journalist, were given to the Library of Congress by his wife, Mary Temple Kleiman, in 2009 and 2011.
Transfers
Photographs and two lithographs have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Robert Kleiman are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified material in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified materials.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1918, Oct. 1 Born, New York, N.Y.
1936 1939 Part-time reporter, editorial writer, and night editor, Michigan Daily, student newspaper, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Mich.
1939 A.B., University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Mich.
1939 1940 Reporter, Washington Post
1941 Reporter, Washington Bureau, New York Journal of Commerce and Commercial Bulletin, covering White House and government, Washington, D.C.
1941 1942 Head of the Far Eastern desk, Press and Radio Division, Foreign Information Service, Office of the Coordinator of Information, Washington, D.C.
1942 Married Elnora Fleurette Haynie (divorced) Syndicate news and feature writer, Office of War Information, Bureau of Overseas Publications, Washington, D.C.
1942 1943 White House correspondent, Voice of America, Office of War Information, Washington, D.C.
1943 1945 Served in the Overseas Branch, Office of War Information, in Australia, Burma, China, India, New Guinea, Philippines, and Territory of Hawaii; chief, Psychological Warfare Team, attached to combat units and headquarters of General Joseph Warren Stilwell, China-Burma-India Theater, 1943-1944; chief of leaflet operations, Hollandia, New Guinea, Tacloban, Leyte Island, Philippines, and Manila, Philippines, attached to U.S. Sixth Army, Psychological Warfare Branch, Southwest Pacific Area, and to the headquarters of General Douglas MacArthur, 1944-1945; attached to Central Pacific Theater, based in Honolulu, Territory of Hawaii, 1945
1945 1962 Editor, U.S. News & World Report; associate editor in Washington, D.C., writing on foreign affairs, 1945-1948; Central European editor and bureau chief, West Germany, 1948-1951; Western European editor and Paris Bureau chief, Paris, France, 1951-1962
1947 Covered Moscow Council of Foreign Ministers, Soviet Union, for U.S. News & World Report; toured Romania, Bulgaria, Hungary, and Austria
pre 1953 Married Jane Eakin (divorced)
1962 1963 Bureau chief and commentator, Columbia Broadcasting System News, Paris, France
1963 1985 Editorial Board member, New York Times, writing about international affairs, principally about United States-European relations
1964 Published Atlantic Crisis: American Diplomacy Confronts a Resurgent Europe. New York: W. W. Norton
1986 Married Mary (Nisbet) Temple
2004, Mar. 22 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Saul Robert Kleiman (1918-2004) span the years 1935-1983, with the bulk of the material dating from 1943 to 1945. The papers are mostly in English and Japanese, with Burmese, Kachin, Shan, and other ethnic Asian languages. The collection is arranged largely according to the groupings established by Kleiman: biographical information, correspondence, Office of War Information files, research files, submissions for awards, and writings, and therein alphabetically by type of material or topic.
The largest portion of the papers relates to Kleiman's service with the United States Office of War Information (OWI) during World War II and pertains to psychological warfare and the use of propaganda in the Far East. The Office of War Information files contain correspondence, memoranda, propaganda in various languages with English translations including leaflets, newspapers, printed matter, broadsides, and ephemera, interrogations of prisoners of war, reports on the effectiveness of propaganda, newsletters, newspaper clippings, and Japanese propaganda in the Philippines. The files also contain personal papers relating to Kleiman's duties and his daily diary. The personal correspondence from the war years also contains information relating to his propaganda activities. Kleiman's writings contain drafts of articles and a radio program he wrote during the war.
On April 3, 1943, Kleiman arrived in New Delhi, India, and was attached to the China-Burma-India Theater (CBI), until June 1, 1944. His papers, however, were grouped under Burma-India. In May-June, 1943, he traveled to Burma and Assam, India, to make a study of the area of CBI-projected operations, to establish liaisons with the American and British military commanders in the area, and to arrange distribution channels for CBI-projected leaflets and other propaganda. Kleiman's multipage report discusses opium distribution in Burma, plans for Burman reconstruction, interviews with British and American military officials, events in the Hukawng Valley and attitudes of the Kachins, propaganda strategy, and the vegetable seed program that dropped seed packets by airplane. He also submitted an intelligence report detailing the speeches and activities of Eddie Rickenbacker during the captain's tour through the Assam area. Also chronicling some of Kleiman's activities in the CBI is his daily diary dating from March 1944 through May 1944. The diary discusses design and production of leaflets, use of Nisei to translate leaflets into Japanese, scheduled drops of leaflets, a radio broadcasting project, use of a public address system to broadcast propaganda, problems with supplies, resettlement of Kachin refugees, and meetings with military personnel. Further material on the CBI is under the heading of leaflets produced in other areas.
Even though China was part of the CBI, Kleiman's files on Yenan, actually Yan'an, were kept separately. Material on this area consists of leaflets and reports. The reports are comprised of intelligence reports on the Eighteenth Group Army of the Chinese that was a combination of the Eighth Route Army of Chinese communists and the New Fourth Army, and a series of "Yenan Reports" submitted by Francis McCracken Fisher, chief of the China Division, OWI, covering psychological warfare findings at and about Yenan from 1944 to 1945.
From June 2, 1944, until May 13, 1945, Kleiman was attached to the Southwest Pacific Area. He surveyed the New Guinea combat zones in June and July, and in early September 1944 arrived in Hollandia, New Guinea, to set up a psychological warfare operation at the headquarters of General Douglas MacArthur and the Sixth Army. There Kleiman was in charge of all forward operations for the OWI in the Southwest Pacific Area and director of leaflet production for the Sixth Army. On October 20, 1944, soon after General MacArthur's landing, Kleiman also landed at Red Beach on Leyte Island in the Philippines. He put on the first Voice of Freedom radio broadcast from the Apache (radio broadcasting ship). Propaganda operations were then moved inland to Tacloban. The close timing of his arrival in New Guinea and his landing on Leyte Island is probably why Kleiman combined the two areas in his files. Material consists of leaflets, correspondence, reports, interrogations of prisoners of war, radio broadcasts, and the basic military plan for psychological warfare in the Southwest Pacific Area. Under the heading of Leyte Island, Philippines, are propaganda newspapers and bulletins produced in the Philippines including the Leyte Shimbun, Leyte-Samar Bulletin, Leyte-Samar Free Philippines, and the Voice of Victory.
On February 8, 1945, Kleiman flew into the Philippine capital of Manila where he stayed until May 13. Material relating to his efforts there includes leaflets and the newspapers Manila Free Philippines and Airborne Edition Free Philippines. Of interest among the usual reports on the effectiveness of the leaflets and Japanese morale is a report on Chinese guerrilla organizations on Luzon and their activities.
The Office of War Information files also contain a group of uncategorized material, scrapbooks, and propaganda from the Asian and European theaters of war. Items in the uncategorized material, consisting of documents either designated by Kleiman as miscellaneous or found loose, are the same type of material housed in the categorized files. In all probability, the loose items were originally part of the categorized material. The scrapbooks were presented to personnel who had worked in propaganda in the Far East and contain runs of propaganda leaflets and newspapers. Propaganda from both theaters of war include leaflets, broadsides, magazines, pamphlets, and ephemeral items (called novelties by Kleiman) that include matchbooks, matchboxes, leaves of soap, and sewing kits, all marked with propaganda.
A large part of the personal correspondence relates to Kleiman's activities during World War II. There are letters to and from his first wife, Elnora H. Kleiman, with friends serving in the war and at home, and with his colleagues in the OWI. The correspondence with his colleagues is the same type Kleiman filed in the Office War Information files and often discusses propaganda and the war. Of interest are discussions on how to phrase propaganda so that conquered peoples understand that the Americans are freeing them from the Japanese and not from European colonizers. Correspondents include Frederic S. "Fritz" Marquardt, Barbara R. "Bobbe" Monroe, and Marshall Darrow "Marsh" Shulman.
Rounding out the collection are clippings of articles written by Kleiman from 1935 to 1955, biographical material, and his research files for articles written after the war concerning United States-European relations.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material or topic and therein alphabetically by type of material or topic.
Container List
- Biographical information, 1935-1945, 1962-1964, 1971, 1983 See also Container 8, Personal file (Box 1)
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Business (Box 1)
    - Incoming, 1954-1956 (Box 1)
    - Flieger, Harold W., and John R. Fleming (Box 1)
      - Memoranda from, 1955-1957, (4 folders) (Box 1)
      - Memoranda to, 1955-1957, (4 folders) (Box 1)
    - Outgoing, 1953-1957 (Box 1)
  - Personal (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1)
      - 1939-1944, (3 folders) (Box 1)
      - 1945, (1 folder) (Box 1, Box 2)
      - 1946-1948 (Box 2)
      - circa 1940s (Box 2)
      - 1953-1983, (6 folders) (Box 2)
    - Kleiman, Elnora H. (Box 2)
      - From, 1943-1945, (3 folders) (Box 2)
      - To (Box 2)
        - 1943 (Box 2)
        - 1944-1945, (2 folders) (Box 3)
- Office of War Information files (Box 3)
  - Background information on Japan, 1939-1944 (Box 3)
  - Brisbane, Australia, leaflets and comic book, 1944, undated See also Oversize (Box 3)
  - Burma-India (Box 3)
    - General, 1942-1945, undated (Box 3)
    - Leaflets (Box 3)
      - In Burmese, Kachin, and Shan, 1944, (2 folders) (Box 3)
      - In Chinese, 1944 (Box 3)
      - In Japanese, 1944-1945, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3)
    - Miscellany, circa 1944-1946 (Box 3)
    - Organizational charts, 1943-1944 (Box 3)
    - "PW Interrogations of Japanese Prisoners-of-War: Northern Burma," 1944 (Box 3)
    - Report on first trip to Burma and travel in India, 1943 (Box 4)
    - Reports, 1945, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Daily diary of Kleiman, 1943, Feb.-Mar.; and 1944, Mar.-May See also Classified (Box 4)
  - Hollandia, New Guinea, and Leyte Island, Philippines (Box 4)
    - General (Box 4)
      - 1944 See also Classified, (5 folders) (Box 4)
      - circa 1944-circa 1945 (Box 5)
      - 1945
    - Leaflets, 1944-1945 See also Oversize (Box 5)
  - Japanese propaganda in Philippines (Box 5)
    - General, circa 1942-circa 1945 See also Oversize, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Jose P. Santos Collection, 1942, undated See Oversize (Box 5)
  - Leaflets produced in other areas (Box 5)
    - Office of War Information, Central Pacific Operations, 1944, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Psychological Warfare Division, Southeast Asia Command, undated (Box 5)
    - Psychological Warfare Team, U.S. Army Forces, China-Burma-India, 1944, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Leyte Island, Philippines (Box 6)
    - An Lantawan, 1939, Feb. 25 See Oversize (Box 6)
    - General, 1942 (Box 6)
    - Leyte Shimbun, 1942, Aug.19-1943, Jan. 30 See Oversize (Box 6)
    - Leyte-Samar Bulletin, 1944, May 27-Oct. 8 See Oversize (Box 6)
    - Leyte-Samar Free Philippines, 1944, Oct. 29-1945, Feb. 15 See Oversize (Box 6)
    - Tanauan, 1942, May 17 (Box 6)
    - Voice of Victory, 1942, Mar. 16-May 13 (Box 6)
  - Manila, Philippines (Box 6)
    - Airborne Edition Free Philippines, 1945, Mar. 25-May 6 (Box 6)
    - General, 1945, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Leaflets, 1944-1945 (Box 6)
    - Manila Free Philippines, 1945, Feb. 9-May 11 See Oversize (Box 6)
  - Miscellany (Box 6)
    - Clippings (Box 6)
      - General, 1946, undated (Box 6)
      - Office of War Information, 1945 (Box 6)
    - Foreign currency, 1940-1943, undated (Box 7)
    - Fragment, 1944 (Box 7)
    - Propaganda from Asian and European theaters of war including ephemeral items, circa 1942-circa 1945 See also Oversize, (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - Newspapers for Japanese, News of the Week ( Ji Ji Shu Ho ) and Parachute News ( Rakkasan News ), 1944-1945 (Box 8)
    - General (Box 8)
    - Leaflets (Box 8)
  - Office of the Coordinator of Information, Kleiman's memoranda on Franklin D. Roosevelt's press conferences, 1941-1942, (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - Personal file, 1942-1945 See also Container 1, Biographical information, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Plans for landing in Japan, 1945 (Box 8)
  - Printed matter (Box 8)
    - Allied Translator and Interpreter Section, Southwest Pacific Area (Box 8)
      - Enemy publications, 1944-1945 (Box 8)
      - Research reports, 1944-1945, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Office of War Information (Box 9)
      - Broadsides (X-3 and X-5), circa 1943-circa 1945 See Oversize (Box 9)
      - Free Philippines (magazine), 1945 (Box 9)
      - Leaflet Newsletter, 1945, (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - Outpost News, 1944-1945, (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - Philippine Digest, circa 1943 (Box 9)
      - Selections from the Philippine Hour, circa 1944 (Box 10)
    - Office of the Military Secretary, Psychological Warfare Branch, General Headquarters, 1945 (Box 10)
    - United Nations, Military Reports of the United Nations, 1943 (Box 10)
    - United States Eighth Army, Psychological Warfare Weekly Report, 1945 (Box 10)
    - United States Fifth Army, Functions of the 5th Army Combat Propaganda Team, 1944 (Box 10)
    - United States Sixth Army (Box 10)
      - Interrogation Report No. 0447, 1945 (Box 10)
      - Psychological Warfare Weekly Report, 1945 (Box 10)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 10)
    - Office of War Information, Central Pacific Operations, 1945 (Box 10)
      - Pages 1-11, (11 folders) (Box 10)
      - Pages 12-82, and front cover See Oversize (Box 10)
    - Psychological Warfare Branch, General Headquarters, Southwest Pacific Area (Box 10)
      - Pages i-ii, 85-111, and enclosed letter See Oversize (Box 10)
      - Pages (Box 10)
        - 1-45, (44 folders) (Box 10)
        - 46-84, (29 folders) (Box 11)
  - Uncategorized material, 1944-1945, undated See also Oversize, (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - United States Eighth Army, leaflet, 1945 (Box 11)
  - United States Sixth Army (Box 11)
    - Leaflets for Philippines, 1944-1945, (3 folders) (Box 11)
    - Maps of leaflet drops in Philippines, circa 1944 See Oversize (Box 11)
  - Yenan (Yan'an, China) (Box 12)
    - Leaflets, circa 1944-circa 1945, (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - Reports and psychological warfare suggestions, 1944-1945 See also Classified, (5 folders) (Box 12)
- Research files (Box 12)
  - Interview notes, 1973, (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Jean Monnet and the Action Committee for the United States of Europe, 1958-1963, (3 folders) (Box 12)
  - John F. Kennedy visit to Italy, 1963 (Box 13)
- Submissions for awards, 1967-1969, 1976 (Box 13)
- Writings (Box 13)
  - Articles (Box 13)
    - Clippings (Box 13)
      - Journal of Commerce and Commercial Bulletin, New York, 1941, (6 folders); (2 folders) (Box 13, Box 14)
      - Lincoln Log, 1935 (Box 14)
      - Michigan Daily, 1936-1939, undated, (5 folders) (Box 14)
      - Miscellany, 1939 (Box 14)
      - New York Times, 1965-1975 (Box 14)
      - U.S. News & World Report, 1946-1948, 1954-1955, (5 folders) (Box 14)
      - Washington Post, 1939-1941, (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Drafts (Box 15)
      - "Corregidor---After the Surrender; by Catherine Nau as Told to Robert Kleiman," circa 1945 (Box 15)
      - "A Day in Leyte," circa 1944 (Box 15)
      - "Leaflet Handling of Surrender Negotiations, August 10-12," 1945 (Box 15)
      - "Liberation and Sardines," 1945 (Box 15)
      - "MacArthur Petition," circa 1944 (Box 15)
      - "United America Fights," 1942 (Box 15)
  - Radio script, "POW Program," 1945 (Box 15)
  - Reports on Europe, 1949-1952 (Box 15)
- Office of War Information files (Box CL 1)
  - Daily diary of Kleiman, 1944, Apr. 5-8 (Container 4) (Box CL 1)
  - Hollandia, New Guinea, and Leyte Island, Philippines (Box CL 1)
    - General (Box CL 1)
      - 1944, Sept. (Box CL 1)
        - "The Japanese Emperor and the War," 1944, Sept. 8 (Container 4) (Box CL 1)
      - 1944, Nov. (Box CL 1)
        - "An Appeal to the Japanese People," 1944, Nov. 14 (Container 4) (Box CL 1)
  - Yenan (Yan'an, China) (Box CL 1)
    - Reports and psychological warfare suggestions (Folder 5 of 5) (Box CL 1)
      - "Translation Series #38. An Appeal to the Japanese People (an open letter) on the Occasion of the Sixth Anniversary of the China Incident," 1944, Nov. 14 (Container 12) (Box CL 1)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Office of War Information files (Box OV 1)
    - Brisbane, Australia, leaflets and comic book (Box OV 1)
      - Comic book, "The Nightmares of Lieutenant Ichi or Juan Posong Gives Ichi the Midnight Jitters," undated (Container 3) (Box OV 1)
    - Hollandia, New Guinea, and Leyte Island, Philippines (Box OV 1)
      - Leaflets (Box OV 1)
        - NICA proclamations: Hollandia and Sarmi (2P6, 3P6) in Dutch and Malay, 1944, Sept. 19 (Container 5) (Box OV 1)
        - NICA Will Govern (1P6) in English, Dutch, and Malay, 1944, Sept. 19 (Container 5) (Box OV 1)
    - Japanese propaganda in the Philippines (Box OV 2)
      - General (Folder 1 of 2) (Box OV 2)
        - Broadsides, magazines, leaflets, leaflet layouts, and other material, circa 1942-circa 1945 (Container 5) (Box OV 2)
      - Jose P. Santos Collection, 1942, undated (Container 5) (Box OV 3)
    - Leyte Island, Philippines (Box OV 4)
      - An Lantawan, 1939, Feb. 25 (Container 6) (Box OV 4)
      - Leyte Shimbun, 1942, Aug.19-1943, Jan. 30 (Container 6) (Box OV 4)
      - Leyte-Samar Bulletin, 1944, May 27-Oct. 8 (Container 6) (Box OV 4)
      - Leyte-Samar Free Philippines, 1944, Oct. 29-1945, Feb. 15 (Container 6) (Box OV 4)
    - Manila, Philippines (Box OV 5)
      - Manila Free Philippines, 1945, Feb. 9-May 11 (Container 6) (Box OV 5)
    - Miscellany (Box OV 5)
      - Propaganda from Asian and European theaters of war including ephemeral items, circa 1942-circa 1945 (Folder 1 of 3) (Box OV 5)
        - Victory (magazine), vol. 1, no. 1, circa 1942, Sept. (Container 7) (Box OV 5)
    - Printed matter (Box OV 6)
      - Office of War Information (Box OV 6)
        - Broadsides (X-3 and X-5), circa 1943-circa 1945 (Container 9) (Box OV 6)
    - Scrapbooks (Box OV 7)
      - Office of War Information, Central Pacific Operations, 1945 (Box OV 7)
        - Pages 12-82, and front cover (Container 10) (Box OV 7)
      - Psychological Warfare Branch, General Headquarters, Southwest Pacific Area, 1945 (Box OV 8)
        - Pages i-ii, 85-111, and enclosed letter (Container 10) (Box OV 8)
    - Uncategorized material (Box OV 9)
      - 1945 (Box OV 9)
        - Newsmap, Southwest Pacific, vol. 3, no. 11, 1945, Mar. 16 (Container 11) (Box OV 9)
    - United States Sixth Army (Box OV 9)
      - Maps of leaflet drops in the Philippines, circa 1944 (Container 11) (Box OV 9)